A Guide to the Gail Baker Collected Materials, 1938-2002
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Gail Baker Collected Materials, 1938-2002
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
RG 346
19 boxes.
Baker, Gail
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Gail Baker between 1994 and 2018.
Biographical/Historical Information
Gail Baker was born and raised in Arlington, Virginia. She grew up in Dominion Hills, attending McKinley Elementary School, Kenmore Middle School, and Washington-Lee High School. In 1994, Baker received a degree in Historic Preservation from Mary Washington College. Baker served on the Arlington County Historical Affairs and Landmark Review Board from 1986-1996, serving as chairman for her final two terms. She helped establish Arlington County's first preservation advocacy group, the Arlington Heritage Alliance, and served as Chairman from 1998-2000. Baker successfully lobbied for the Arlington County Board to institute a Neighborhood Historic District program leading to the designation of Maywood, the county's first multi-property, multi-owner historic district. She wrote numerous guides, outreach pamphlets, and articles on preservation and planned and ran preservation training workshops for Arlington's Architectural Review Board. In addition, Baker prepared successful National Register nominations for Carlin Hall, Fairlington, Holmes Run Acres, and Lost River General Store.
The Historical Affairs and Landmark Review Board (HALRB) was created under the Zoning Ordinance in 1976 to advise the Arlington County Board on historic preservation matters. HALRB consists of a 15-member board appointed for four-year terms by the Arlington County Board. The board nominates properties for local and national historic designation and reviews construction and development plans for locally designated Arlington historic districts.
The National Register of Historic Places (NRHP)was created by the National Historic Preservation Act of 1966 (NHPA) and is the United States' official list of buildings, sites, districts, structures, and objects worthy of preservation. Designation to the NRHP is evaluated under four categories of historical significance: event, person, architecture, and information potential-the majority of properties are considered significant under one or more of the first three categories. Designation on the National Register does not legally protect a site, but it does provide property owners tax incentives and the opportunity to apply for various grants. As of October 2018, Arlington County has 65 properties listed on the National Register.
Scope and Content
RG 346 is a collection of Gail Baker's papers relating to her activities with the Arlington County preservation community. Materials date 1938-2002, with the bulk of the materials dating 1980-2000. The collection is 15.22 linear feet, not including oversize material.
Series 1 holds materials related to historical buildings in Arlington County. These materials include newspaper articles, historical maps and research, and HALRB official documentation and correspondence. Some files in this collection hold only one or two items, while others contain a swath of materials. Files on Arna Valley, Brown-Crossman, Doubleday, Lomax A.M.E. Zion Church, and Walker Chapel contain photographs.
In addition to Historic Landmark and National Register official forms and correspondence, Subseries 1, Carlin Hall, holds photographs and photo negatives of Carlin Hall, as well as extensive research into the history of Carlin Hall. Gail Baker researched and wrote the National Register nomination for Carlin Hall as part of a preservation course at Mary Washington University (then Mary Washington College), which likely accounts for the expanded records on Carlin Hall in comparison to the other historical buildings in this collection, which are found in Subseries 2, Other Historic Buildings.
Series 2 holds materials related to two historic districts: Columbia Pike and Buckingham Village. Subseries 1, Columbia Pike primarily holds studies of the district and revitalization plans, while Subseries 2, Buckingham Village primarily holds correspondence about renovation plans and architectural plans.
Series 3, Historical Sites Surveys and Reports contains surveys and reports on various Arlington County neighborhoods and historic sites. The surveys and reports relate to the land use, history, and archeology of the sites.
Series 4, County Development and Preservation Plans contains surveys and reports on County-wide development plans and initiatives. The reports either originate from an official Arlington County office or a County Task Force. Most materials in this series relate to County development projects and reports, but two County-wide preservation plans are also included.
Series 5, Administrative Materials and Regulations, contains a wide variety of materials related to the Historic Landmark Review Board's work. There are materials that relate to HALRB's outreach including events and pamphlets, as well as materials related to policies that affect historic preservation efforts such as zoning codes and demolition penalties. This series holds HALRB Annual Reports between 1986 and 1992, as well as materials related to the organizations budget, by-laws, and hiring. File 27, Photographic Records of Development Sites, 1985, 1988-1990, does not contain any photographs. Instead, the file holds Arlington County correspondence regarding County photo-documentation of development sites. File 12 contains a photo from the National Historic Preservation Week and a photo from the Boundary Stones Proclamation and File 15 contains three photographs of garden apartments form across the County.
Series 6, Newspapers, contains various newspaper clippings related to preservation and history in Arlington County. There are a few clippings on preservation and history in surrounding areas, as well. S eries 7, Neighborhood Historic District Program, contains Neighborhood Historic District documentation.
Series 8, Robert McAtee Research, contains newspaper clippings, photographs, and articles related to Robert McAtee's research into Arlington's history and particularly his research on Maywood and Cherrydale. These materials were given to Gail Baker by Robert McAtee for her own research.
Arrangement
This collection has five series, with the first two series each split into two subseries. Series 1 holds materials related to historical buildings in Arlington County. Subseries 1, Carlin Hall, is arranged chronologically with undated material at the end arranged by subject matter. All folder titles were created by the archivist. Subseries 2, Other Historic Buildings, is arranged alphabetically and labeled in the manner it was received; portions of folder titles in brackets ([]) have been added by the archivist for clarification.
Series 2, Historical Districts and Neighborhoods, is split into two subseries: Subseries 1, Columbia Pike, and Subseries 2, Buckingham Village. Both are arranged chronologically and any folders labeled by Gail Baker are put into quotes (""); otherwise, the archivist created folder titles for this series.
Series 3 is arranged alphabetically by folder title and Series 4 is arranged chronologically. Folder titles in these series were created by the archivist; folders labeled by Gail Baker are put into quotes (""). Series 5 is arranged alphabetically, and folders are labeled in the manner they were received; portions of folder titles in brackets ([]) and dates after the comma have been added by the archivist for clarification.
Series 6-8 are arranged based on original folder structure. Folders labeled by Gail Baker are put into quotes (""); otherwise, the archivist created folder titles for these series.
There are oversized materials in this collection, which have been moved to appropriate housing. Separation sheets have been added to mark their original placement. An asterisk (*) at the end of the folder title denotes oversize materials found in this location.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Researchers can find related information in RG 22, Arlington County Historical Boards and Commissions, RG 30, Historic Neighborhood and Building Reports, RG 120A Fairlington Historic District, RG 126 Columbia Pike Revitalization Organization Records, RG 130 Arlington County Planning Commission Records, and RG 175 Records of Arlington Heritage Alliance.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Historic buildings; Neighborhoods -- United States.; Arlington (Va.); Arlington County (Va.)
Contents List
- Historical Buildings
  - Carlin Hall
    - Carlin Hall HALRB Certificate of Appropriateness, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Carlin Hall Virginia Historic Landmark Commission Survey Form, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Carlin Hall NRHP Registration Form, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - Carlin Hall Correspondence, 1991-1993 (Box 1)
    - Carlin Hall Park, 1986, 1993-1994, 2000 * (Box 1)
    - Carlin Hall Field Notes, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Mary Washington College Course, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Articles, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Carlin Hall Research (1) (Box 1)
    - Carlin Hall Research (2) (Box 1)
    - Rsearch Notes (Box 1)
    - Gail Baker's Carlin Hall Scholarship (Box 1)
    - Carlin Hall Photographs (Box 1)
    - Carlin Hall Negatives (Box 1)
    - Carlin Slides (Box 2)
  - Other Historic Buildings
    - Alcova (Box 2)
    - Arlington Boulevard/Route 50 (Box 2)
    - Arlington Cemetery (Box 2)
    - Arlington Forest (Box 2)
    - Arlington Hall (Box 2)
    - Arlington House (Box 2)
    - Arlington Post Office* (Box 2)
    - Arlington Village (Box 2)
    - Arna Valley (Box 2)
    - Ashton Heights (Box 2)
    - Aurora Highlands (Addison Heights) (Box 2)
    - Babcock House (Box 2)
    - Ball Cemetery (Box 2)
    - Ball-Sellers House (Box 2)
    - Barcroft Community House* (Box 3)
    - Barcroft National Register Nomination (Box 3)
    - Barcroft Apartments (Box 3)
    - Bluemont (Box 3)
    - Boundary Stones (Box 3)
    - Brandymore Castle (Box 3)
    - Broadview/Lacey House, 5151 14th St. N. (Box 3)
    - Brown-Crossman House (Box 3)
    - Brumback Houses (Box 3)
    - Buckingham (Box 3)
    - Byrne House, 2431 N. Underwood (Box 3)
    - Calvert Manor (Box 3)
    - Mary Carlin House (Box 3)
    - Chain Bridge (Box 3)
    - Cherrydale (Box 3)
    - Cherrydale Fire Department (Box 3)
    - Civil War Trails (Box 3)
    - Clarendon Ballroom (Box 3)
    - Clarendon Citizens' Hall (Box 4)
    - Court House Row (Box 4)
    - Courtlands (N. Danville) (Box 4)
    - Crossman-Grey (Box 4)
    - Custis Estate (Box 4)
    - Custis Parkway (Box 4)
    - Dawson Bailey House (Box 4)
    - Charles Drew House (Box 4)
    - Dominion Hills (Box 4)
    - Doubleday [The Cedars] (Box 4)
    - [Paul Laurence] Dunbar [Mutual] Homes [Association] (Box 4)
    - Dundee, 3731 N. Glebe Rd. (Box 4)
    - East Falls Church (Box 4)
    - Eastman-Fenwick House (Box 4)
    - Fillmore Gardens (Box 4)
    - Fort Myer (Box 4)
    - Fostoria (Box 4)
    - Freedman's Village (Box 5)
    - Gamble House (Box 5)
    - Garden Apartments (Box 5)
    - Glebe House (1) (Box 5)
    - Glebe House (2) (Box 5)
    - Glencarlyn (Box 5)
    - Glenayr Apartments (Box 5)
    - Glenmore (Box 5)
    - Harry Gray House (Box 5)
    - Gray Property, 2146 N. Courthouse Rd. (Box 5)
    - Greathouse Tract (Box 5)
    - Basil Hall House, 1700 N. George Mason Dr. (Box 5)
    - Highview Park (Hall's Hill) (Box 5)
    - Hume Schoool - Arlington History Museum (Box 5)
    - I-66 (Box 5)
    - Iwo Jima (Box 5)
    - Jacobs Tract/Bayeva Castle (Box 5)
    - Jefferson Davis Corridor (Box 5)
    - Dan Kain Building (Box 5)
    - Key Bridge (Box 6)
    - Kirby-Witman (Box 6)
    - Kirby's Garage (Box 6)
    - Lane House (Large Lot Survey) (Box 6)
    - Large Lot Survey (Box 6)
    - Lee Gardens (Box 6)
    - Lomax A.M.E. Zion Church * (Box 6)
    - Luna Park, Elephants (Box 6)
    - Lustron Houses (Box 6)
    - Lyon Park (Box 6)
    - Lyon Village (Box 6)
    - Maury School (1)* (Box 6)
    - Maury School (2) (Box 6)
    - McCreary House, 2231 N. Military Rd. (Box 6)
    - Missionhurst (Box 6)
    - Charles E. Morris House, 4464 N. Old Glebe Rd. (Box 6)
    - Mount Zion Baptist Church (Box 6)
    - Munson House (Box 7)
    - National Airport (Box 7)
    - North Highlands (Box 7)
    - Palisades (Box 7)
    - Parkfairfax (Box 7)
    - Penrose (Box 7)
    - Powhatan Springs (Box 7)
    - Radio Towers (Box 7)
    - Reevesland, 400 N. Manchester (Box 7)
    - Ridgecrest (Box 7)
    - Ristorante Michelangelo (Old Dominion Bank) (Box 7)
    - Rixey Mansion (Box 7)
    - Rosemont National Register Nomination (Box 7)
    - Rosslyn (Box 7)
    - Rosslyn Marker (Box 7)
    - J. Saegmuller House (Box 7)
    - St. George's Church (Box 7)
    - Schools (Box 7)
    - Shirlington (Box 7)
    - Stoneburner House, 6113 Lee Highway (Box 7)
    - Stratford [Junior High School]* (Box 7)
    - Travers Family Graveyard, S. Monroe St. Cemetery (Box 7)
    - Trolley Barn (Box 8)
    - Walker Cabin (Box 8)
    - Walker Chapel (Box 8)
    - Westmont Shopping Center (Box 8)
    - William Willis House, 2801 N. Arizona St. (Box 8)
    - Wilson Blvd. Park * (Box 8)
- Historical Districts and Neighborhoods
  - Columbia Pike
    - Columbia Pike Commercial Corridor Study, 1985 * (Box 8)
    - Land Use and Zoning Study Draft, June 1986 (Box 8)
    - Columbia Pike 2000, June 1986 (Box 8)
    - Columbia Pike 2000 Executive Summary, June 1988 (Box 8)
    - Columbia Pike History 1988, n.d. (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1986-2001 (Box 8)
    - Columbia Pike: A Vision for the Future, 1998 (Box 8)
    - "Columbia Pike Revitalization" Public Outreach, 1987, 2000-2002 (Box 8)
    - Columbia Pike Initiative, June 2001 (Box 8)
    - Columbia Pike Revitalization Plan, 2002 * (Box 9)
    - Columbia Pike HALRB, 2002 (Box 9)
    - Columbia Pike Revitalization District Form-Based Code, November 2002 * (Box 9)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box 9)
  - Buckingham Village
    - "Buckingham 1985-1991," 1938-1940, 1948, 1958, 1968, 1985-1986 (Box 9)
    - "Buckingham 1985-1991," 1985-1990 (Box 9)
    - "Buckingham 1985-1991," January - June 19191 (Box 9)
    - "Buckingham 1985-1991," July 1991 (Box 9)
    - "Buckingham 1985-1991," August - October 1991 (Box 9)
    - "Buckingham 1985-1991," Demographic Survey, December 23, 1991 (Box 9)
    - "Buckingham Safeway," 1990-1991 (Box 9)
    - "Buckingham - National Register/PIF," 1991 (Box 10)
    - "Buckingham," 1991-1992 (Box 10)
    - Buckingham, 1992 (1) (Box 10)
    - Buckingham, 1992 (2) (Box 10)
    - Buckingham, 1993 (1) (Box 10)
    - Buckingham, 1993 (2) (Box 10)
    - Buckingham Historic District Guidelines, June 1993 (Box 10)
    - Buckingham, 1994 (Box 11)
    - HALRB Buckingham Historic District Guidelines and Review, November 1994 (Box 11)
    - Paradigm Development Company Certificate of Appropriateness, March 1995 (1)* (Box 11)
    - Paradigm Development Company Certificate of Appropriateness, March 1995 (2) (Box 11)
    - Buckingham, March - May 1995 * (Box 11)
    - Buckingham, June - August 1995 * (Box 11)
    - Buckingham, September - December 1995 (Box 11)
    - Paradigm Buckingham Appeal, 1995 (Box 11)
    - Buckingham, 1996 (Box 12)
    - Village 3 Rehabilitation Certificate of Appropriateness Application (Box 12)
- Historical Sites Surveys and Reports
  - Abingdon Plantation and Washington National Airport, 1988, 1989 (Box 12)
  - Arlington Arts Center Schematic Design, 1990-1991 (Box 12)
  - Clarendon, 1988-1989 (Box 12)
  - Cherrydale Hardware Store and Cherrydale Masonic Lodge Building, 1988 (Box 12)
  - Crystal City, 1989 (Box 12)
  - East Falls Church, 1984, 1987 (Box 12)
  - Fairlington-Shirlington, 1987 (Box 12)
  - Four Mile Run Bus Garage, 1992 (Box 13)
  - George Washington Memorial Parkway, 1990 (Box 13)
  - Lee Highway, 1989 (Box 13)
  - Lee Highway Cherrydale Revitalization Plan, May 1992 (Box 13)
  - Lee Highway Cherrydale Revitalization Plan, April 1994 (Box 13)
  - Potomac Palisades, 1990, 1992 (Box 13)
  - Rosslyn-Ballston Corridor Review, 1988-1989, 2001 * (Box 13)
  - School Historic District Survey, 1992 (Box 13)
- County Development and Preservation Plans
  - Preservation Plan for Arlington County, 1983, 1984 (Box 14)
  - Development in the Metro Corridors, 1985 (Box 14)
  - Task Force on Housing and Neighborhoods Report, 1986 (Box 14)
  - Task Force on the Development Process, 1987, 1988 (Box 14)
  - Comprehensive Community Improvement Program, 1989 (Box 14)
  - Open Space Task Force, 1989-1994, 2002 (Box 14)
  - 1990 Open Space Report and 1994 Open Space Master Plan (Box 14)
  - Phase One Architectural Survey Report, 1996 (Box 14)
  - Neighborhood Traffic Calming Committee Reports, 1998, 2000 (Box 14)
  - "Virginia Square Sector Plan," 2003 (Box 14)
- Administrative Materials and Regulations
  - Arlington Zoning Code Amendment 31A, 1993 (Box 14)
  - Bicentennial Commission, 1976, 2000-2001 (Box 14)
  - Budget, 1986-2002 (Box 14)
  - [Historic] Burial Regs. [Regulations], 1991, 1993 (Box 15)
  - Business Relocation Study, 1987-1989 (Box 15)
  - By-Laws - HARLB, 1988-1995 (Box 15)
  - CLG [Certified Local Government], 1986-1994 (Box 15)
  - Conflict of Interest/Financial Disclosure/Advisory Group Policies, 1991-1994 (Box 15)
  - Correspondence (Misc.), 1988-1995 (Box 15)
  - Demolition Penalty, 1990-1991 (Box 15)
  - Development Moratorium, 1988-1989 (Box 15)
  - Events: County Fair, Annual Training, 1988-1995 (Box 15)
  - [HALRB Annual Reports, 1986-1992] (Box 15)
  - HALRB Pamphlets, 1991, n.d. (Box 16)
  - Fair Exhibit HALRB, 1992-1993 * (Box 16)
  - Governor's Commission, 1987-1989 (Box 16)
  - ISTEA [Intermodal Surface Transportation Efficiency Act], 1992-1993 (Box 16)
  - Design Awards, 1999-2002 (Box 16)
  - Land Trust, 2000-2002 (Box 16)
  - Library Records (Box 16)
  - List of Historic Districts and Inventory* (Box 16)
  - Markers and Plaques, 1988-1994, 2000 (Box 16)
  - Master CoA [Certificate of Appropriateness], 1992 (Box 16)
  - Metal Detectors 1991 (Box 16)
  - [HALRB] Motto, Eisenberg [Speech], 1987 (Box 16)
  - Naming Policy, 1971, 1988, 2001 (Box 16)
  - Photographic Records of Development Sites, 1985, 1988-1990 (Box 16)
  - Researching House Histories (Box 16)
  - Resumes, 1986-1993 (Box 16)
  - Section 31A, amended 1990, 1991 (Box 16)
  - [NHPA] Section 106, 1999 (Box 17)
  - Site Plan [Regulation], 1986 (Box 17)
  - State Grants, 2000 (Box 17)
  - Subdivision Ordinance, 1989-1994 (Box 17)
  - Tax Relief/Incentives, 1979, 1986-1994, 1998, 2000-2001 (Box 17)
  - Utility Undergrounding in Historic Districts, 1991 (Box 17)
  - VDOT Memo of Understanding, 1990-1991 (Box 17)
  - Work Program, 1988-1998 (Box 17)
  - 100 Important Historic Sites List, 2001 (Box 17)
- Newspaper Articles
  - "Neighborhood Sun Series - 1955 " (Box 17)
  - "Sun Gazette 2001 Bicentennial Series" (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous Articles (1) (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous Articles (2) (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous Articles (3) (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous Articles (4) (Box 18)
- Neighborhood Historic District Program
  - NHDs (1) (Box 18)
  - NHDs (2) (Box 18)
- Robert McAtee Research
  - McAtee(1) (Box 19)
  - McAtee(2) (Box 19)
  - McAtee(3) (Box 19)
  - McAtee(4) (Box 19)
  - McAtee(5) (Box 19)
  - McAtee(6) (Box 19)